Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 3 -- Letters to Franklin 1778 April-December Mss.B.F85inventory03
American Philosophical Society
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778; A.L.S. 1p.; Durand, -----. Paris
    While passing through Turin, the Baron de Choiseul, the French Ambassador, entrusted him with the enclosed for Franklin; desires to pay his respects at the earliest favorable moment.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [c. March 14, 1779]; A.L.S. 1p.; Dusaulx, Jean. Paris
    Deputed by his colleague, M. Anquetil Duperron, to present Franklin with his book, "Legislation Orientale."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.N. in 3d P. 1p.; de Flamarens, Marquis
    Requesting Franklin to forward a letter to a French officer in America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.N. in 3d P. 1p.; Flavigny, Madame de
    Expects him on Saturday, will wait for him in the Tuilleries.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.N. in 3d P. 1p.; Flavigny, Madame de
    Reminds Franklin he is to take tea with her on Wednesday.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778?; L.S. 1p.; De Frëy, -----
    Requests Franklin to deliver a letter to his brother, who is captain in Count Pulaski's Legion.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, N. 3p.; Genet, Edme Jacques, d.1781
    Suggesting to Franklin a way of receiving his two Gazettes regularly from London, by having them addressed to " Monsieur Genet, à Versailles."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1778?]; A.L.S. 1p.; Gika, Alexandre Andronique
    Wishes to know if it would be possible for a Jew to be named consul for the United States at Marseilles.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778?; A.L.S. 3p.; Gray, D-----. Paris
    Begging his assistance to procure him a position as tutor, or work as a translator.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1778?]; Mem. 3p.; frères, Gregoire. Havre
    Applies for the appointment of Consul for the United States in Normandy.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, Mem. 1p.; Guiraud, Nicolas
    Applies for the appointment of Consul for the United States at Cette. Is recommended by M. Le Veillard.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1780?]; 3d P. 1p.; Holker, John
    Begging the loan, for a few days, of the latest Paris Journal.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, D. 3p.; Holtzer, Antoine
    Certificate authorizing him to brew and sell the new kind of beer which he has discovered.
  - to Memoir., [After June 20 [1778?]; Mem. 1p.; Jones, Capt. John Paul
    Asks whether the "Ranger" should depart before her prizes are realized; whether the advances must be deducted; and whether it is not inexpedient for a ship that sails slow and is of trifling force to pursue a track where there is almost a certainty of meeting with the enemy's fast-sailing ships of superior force.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1778?]; A.L. 8p.; Jones, Capt. John Paul
    Insubordination on the "Ranger"; conduct of Lieutenant Simpson which led up to his imprisonment.
    (Incomplete.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1778?]; 1p.; Jones, Capt. John Paul
    The prisoners taken by the "Ranger."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [Crica 1778.]; N. in 3d P. 1p.; Kéralio, Agathon Guynement, chevalier de
    Thanking Messrs. Frankinn for the news they sent him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [Jan.? 1778]; Mem. 2p.; Kerguelen, M. de
    Is a navigator and ship captain; offers his services to the United States Congress of fit out a vessel to wage war on English shipping.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778. ----- 19; A.L.S. 2p.; Kermorvan, Chevalier de
    Embarrasing situation in which his voyage to America has placed him; thinks Franklin will see the justice of making him some amends; desires permission to obtain a certain sum from Franklin's bankers every week, for his necessary expenses while in Paris.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1778]; A.L.S. 1p.; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves, marquis de, 1757-1834
    Requesting a letter of recommendation to Congress for a relative of hers who is about to sail for America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.N. in 3d P. 1p.; La Rochefoucauld, Louis Alexandre, duc de
    Sending a letter which he has written to Captain Jones an account of his conversation with M. de Sartine.
  - to The American Commissioners., [1778] Sunday; A.L.S. 1p.; Lee, Arthur. Paris
    No alteration taken place as yet with respect to the frigate "Bordeaux." Girard's advice concerning M. Beaumarchais's account.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778; D. 1p.; Lee, William
    Proposed receipt for certain papers taken from the trunk of Thomas Morris, deceased.
    A. E. by Dr. Franklin that he had declined to sign it.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1778 Sept. 9]; A.N. in 3d P. 1p.; Le Roy, Jean Baptiste
    Inquires if Franklin has received any news about Count d'Estaing.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1778]; A.L.S. 1p.; Le Roy, Jean Baptiste
    Asking Franklin, his grandson and Mr. Adams to dine with the Comte de Maillebois before the meeting of the Academy.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 3p.; Le Roy, Jean Baptiste
    Sends report on the project of M. de la Blancherie. Asks leave to bring Abbé Le Noble to dinner. Requests Dr. Franklin to send him Ingen Housz's observations on priestley's discovery relatives to coal (carbon).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1778.]; A.L.S. 2p.; Le Roy, Jean Baptiste
    The report on the project of M. de la Blancherie will be submitted to the Academy.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1778.]; A.L.S. 3p.; Le Roy, Jean Baptiste
    The Commissioners appointed by the Academy will dine at his house, Hopes Franklin will not fail to attend the dinner.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.N.S. 1p.; Le Roy, Jean Baptiste
    Asking if Franklin has not the reminder of Count de Lacepède's manuscript on electricity.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, L.S. 1p.; Le Roy, Louis Gabriel
    Is a furniture maker and machinist; offers his services to the American Commissioners.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [c. 1778? Dec.]; Diss. 8p.; Lestume and Coquillon. Brest
    Concerning the capture of certain American vessels.
  - to Commissioners., [march 1778]; L. 5p.; de Longchamps, -----. Versailles
    His advantures and misfortunes while in the service of the United States. Was formerly a licutenant in the Guadeloupe Legion, came to Cambridge, Mass., Where he offered his services to the American Commander. Was wounded and taken prisoner in the first engagement with the English. Imprisoned for a long time in Boston and afterwards in England.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [April 4 1780]; A.L.S. 1p.; MacCreery, William
    Has newspapers and journals of Congress for Franklin, received from Mr. Lovell. Message to Mr. Adams.
    [First part missing.]
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1778.]; A.L.S. 1p.; Malherbe, Dom. Abbaye de St. Germain
    Recommending to Franklin a young surgeon of great talent.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1778]; A.L.S. 1p.; Lucé, Chevalier de Marolles
    His distress and want; his wife dangerously ill; is without money or food; begs Franklin to give him a few louis.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 ----- 4; A.L.S. 2p.; Melmoth, Courtney. Paris
    Offering his services as Secretary to the American Commissioners; has refused "The British bread of bribery"; desires above all things a connection with cause of America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1778?]; A.L.S. 2p.; Merckle, J P
    Announcing his intention to give the weighty commission entrusted to him to the House of Messrs. Ambrosius Pool and Co. who are from Switzerland and may be considered totally out of all connection with the E[nglish] nation; has not the least doubt that they will give complete satisfaction in every sense. Report that the Dutch merchantmen going to their colonies will get a convoy of Dutch men-of-war.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [Before April 23, 1778]; A.L.S. 1p.; Merechy, Marshal de
    Accepts Franklin's proposal. Requests him to advise his grandson, Mr. Lee and Mr. Adams to that effect.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1778?]; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Meuricoffre and Co. Naples
    Asking for position of American Consul-General, at Naples for M. Meuricoffre.
  - to W.T.F., before 1777 Jan. 13; N. in 3d P. 1p.; de Milly, Count
    lnviting Dr. Franklin and his grandson to dine with him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1780-1781]; A.L.in 3d P. 1p.; Morand, Jean François Clément
    Inquiring about a coal mine near Newcastle which is described, in a volume of the [Philosophical] "Transactions" for the year 1676, as being on fire; whether it still exists. I
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1778.]; Mem. 14p.; Veuve Morel et Fills, Messrs
    Are merchants of Dunkirk; give an account of services rendered by them to the United States and its subjects and ask that they be given charge of American business interests at Dunkirk.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1778?]; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Petrie, -----. Paris
    Report from London of the "Randolph" and "Columbus" being sunk by the "Yarmouth," man-of-war, and of the "Alfred" being taken by the "Ariadnc" and "Ceres."
  - to American Commissioners., Mem. 3p.; Captain Pickerin
    Concerning the prizes taken by his corsair "The Hamden".
  - to The American Commissioners, [1778?]; L.S. James Falls, Gunner, et al. 3p.; The Peyty Officers on board the Ranger
    Expressing dissatisfaction with Captain [John Paul] Jones and requesting to be permitted to return to the United States.
  - to The American Commissioners, 1778 May 30; L.S. Elijah Hall, et al. 2p.; Several Officers on board the Ranger
    Protesting against the treatment and imprisonment of Lieutenant Simpson and testifying to his good character.
  - to The American Commissioners., [1788]; A.L.S. 12p.; Raudière, J. D. R. de
    A poor poet; craves assistance to enable him to finish an epic poem against the English and to print his other works; desires to finish his days in America.
  - to The American Commissioners., [1778?]; Verses. 1p.; Raudière, J. D. R. de
    Addressing his poem "The Ameriquiade" to Franklin, Deane and Lee. Hope they will do something to alleviate his distress.
  - to American Commissioners, before [1778 May 16]; L. 2p.; de Basmarin et Raimbaux, Recules. Bordeaux
    Reciting their services to the United States during the war, as merchants and shippers. Wish to obtain from the King an armed frigate to convoy their vessels to North America. Hope the Deputies from Congress will help them in their purpose.
  - to American Commissioners., [1778.]; A.L.S. 2p.; Riou, Pierre
    Concerning the sale of the prize made by the "Hampden"; action taken by the Admiralty in the affair; need of Franklin's powerful protection.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, c. 1778; A.L. 3p.; Sarsfield, Guy-Claude, comte de
    Making certain alterations in his plan for Spanish reading, proposed to Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, c. 1778; A.L.S. 1p.; Scott, George. Paris
    Desiring a pass from Marseilles to Naples.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1782.]; A.L.S. 3p.; Shuttleworth, John. Paris
    Advantages of going straight to New York; desires a few lines to General Washington which will enable him to pass through the lines.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1778 May - June]; L. 2p.; Stragham, William
    Late master of the ship "Lord Chatham," of Dublin, a prisoner at Brest; petitions to be released with his son-in-law and allowed to return to Dublin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1778? March]; Doc. 2p.; Taillet, Philippe
    Application to be appointed Consul, for the United States, at Rouen. Endorsed by Mme. de Forbach, the Dowager Duchess Des Deux-Pont, and Chevalier de Keralio.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L.S. 2p.; Tarteron, -----. Ganges
    Begging Franklin's influence with M. Necker to procure for him a certain situation. Owes his reputation as a poet to his verses on the insurgents.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, L. in 3d P. 1p.; Teissier, Le Sieur
    Is a surgeon of the Salpétrière Hospital at Paris; offers his services to the United States.
  - to The American Commissioners, [1778?]; A.L.S. 2p.; Thompson, Thomas. L'Orient
    His approaching departure on a cruise; personal civilities received from the French authorities cannot alone for the insult offered the States in his person as their officer.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1778?]; L.S. 2p.; Tramblay, -----
    Offers to act as correspondent or agent for the United States at Brest.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1778]; A.N. 1p.; Vaughan, Benjamin
    So soon as the opportunity of conversing, with a certain man is over, will meet him publicly and tell him how much he reveres him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [Circa 1778]; A.L.S. 1p.; Vaughan, Benjamin. Paris
    Desiring an hour's conversation with Franklin concerning his brother and himself; would like to have the meeting at a neutral place, until he has gone through the ceremony of seeing Lord Stormont; Franklin aware of his reasons for sending in his name to Lord Stormont.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1778?]; A.N. 1p.; Le Veillard, Louis Guillaume
    Inquires if he has received his despatches and if he has any news about Count d'Estating.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1778]; A.L.S. 1p.; Le Veillard, Louis Guillaume
    Asks for the Comedy of the Conscious Lovers, which he had forgotten to take with him.
  - to Silas Deane, [before 1778 April 1]; N. in 3d P. 1p.; Villiers, Louis-Pierre Dufourny de
    Wishes to know at what time Franklin comes to Paris, so as to confer with him on American affairs.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 July 19; A.L.S. 1p.; Wharton, Samuel. Monday
    Mail Packet taken by an American privateer and carried into Dunkirk. Believes the news of General Lincoln's success to be authentic. Thanking him for the perusal of the inclosed foolish paper; presumably written by a Junto of American Tories, tools of Lord George Germain.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1778?]; A.L.S. 1p.; Wildrik, W
    Begs for a reply to his letter of December 26th, 1777.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1778?]; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, John
    Concerning a bond debt due him from his brother in Boston.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, A.L. 2p.; --------, -------
    Proposes a plan to prevent corruption and venality in judges and others who administer justice. How to expedite law-suits and avoid unnecessary expense. Judges should be elected by the people and receive a fixed salary. System adopted in Switzerland.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778?; L. 1p.; Laurmuas, the Comte de
    Congratulation on his arrival with intelligence of the first moment. Informs him that M. de Morande is Secretary to M. Beaumarchais, and brother of a refugee of the same name in London; Charles Parker, of Somerset street, for some times past and now in paris, initimate with all three, conveys (by lord stormont's messenger) to Lord Mansfield all the transaction of the court of France with America. C------m----was to go to England, but it was found that Mr. P-------F------could more conveniently go to France. Too wise to neglect this because anonymous.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 April 10; Verses. 3p.; A--------, L-----. Girca
    "The horse and his master." Song composed for and sung at the entertainment given to Franklin and his friends by M. Brillon.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, Verses 1p.; --------,-----
    "To the Americans." On thier stuggles against England.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [Cicra 1778.]; Mem. and verses. 11p.; --------,-----
    Reflections on the war between England and the American Colonists and stanzas to the latter.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1778.]; L. 2p.; --------,-----
    The sister of Captain Fray [De Frey?] serving in the American army, who is in distressed circumstances in France, petitions Franklin to help her by procuring promotion for her husband in the French army.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, Diss. 4P.; -----, -----
    The proposition of the English Ministry for peace with the United Colonies, and the advantages of an alliance with the Houses of Bourbon and of Brandenburg against the disadvantages of a treaty with England.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, Diss. 5p.; -----, -----
    A proposition for peace.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, Mem. 2p.; -----, -----
    Proposal to furnish supplies and munitions of war to the United States on certain conditions.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [C 1779 March 27]; Mem. 1p.; Bondfield, John. list of Ca-nnon
    List and particulars of cannon which could be purchased at Ferrol, Spain.
  - to Count Cheenyshev, 1773 Mar. 10; L.S. 2p.; Golgoeney, Prince Vasily
    Recommending de Wiebel.
    (In Russian.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 November 21; A.L.S. 2p.; Taylor, Jesse. Belfast
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 November 22; A.L.S. 3p.; D' Aire, ------. Alby
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 November 23; A.L.S. 1p.; Pickerin, Capt Thomas. Brest
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 November 24; A.L.S. 1p.; Ridley, Matthew. Nantes
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 November 24; A.L.S. 2p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 November 24; A.L.S. 2p.; La Cadette, Romaneix. Limoges
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 November 26; A.L.S. 2p.; Bordot, L. Versailles
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 November 26; A.L.S. 2p.; de Monchy, S. Rotterdam
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 November 27; A.L.S. 3p.; Kéralio, Agathon Guynement, chevalier de
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 November 28; A.L.S. 3p.; Bondfield, John. Bordeaux
  - to Messrs. Franklin and Adams., 1778 November 28; L.S. 1p.; Lee, Arthur. Chaillot
    Not having any notice of their altered plans, he and Count de Vergennes waited for them in vain till five o'clock. The Count wishes to know just when the ships will ready to sail, so that he may do all in his power to obtain the desired convoy.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 November 26; A.L.S. 2p.; Cadet, -----
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 November 28; A.L.S. 1p.; Gilbank, John. Nantes
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 November 29; A.L.S. 1p.; d'Aubigne, Marquis. Passy
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 November 29; A.L.S. 1p.; Roumallard, ----- Perdriel. Mortrée
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 November 30; A.L.S. 2p.; Le Baron, ------. Dieppe
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 November 30; A.L.S. 4p.; D'Amblé, Abbé. La Claireau
    A plan of establishing well-equipped forges and arsenals in Pennsylvania; question of bringing the workmen over from France; his knowledge of this industry.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 November 30; A.L.S. 1p.; Masseure, Francis-Geron. St. Malo
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 November 15; A.L.S. 1p.; Amiel, Charlotte. Auteuil
  - to The American Commissioners., After [1778 November 17]; A.L.S. 4p.; Smith, Dr James
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 December 1; L.S. 1p.; Gleed, Thomas et al. Combourg
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 December 1; A.L.S. 1p.; de Vienne, Field Marshall Comte. Paris
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 December 1; L.S. 2p.; Meunier,------. Paris
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 December 1; A.L.S. 4p.; Holtzer, Antoine. Colmar
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 December 2; A.L.S. 1p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Enclosing a copy of Amsterdam's Resolutions, à propos of increasing the army in Holland (22 p.); intrigues of the English party aim to increase the army of Holland at the expense of her navy.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 December 2; A.L.S. 8p.; de Daillens, Weiss. Berne
    His hatred of oppression and tyranny; his ardent desire to serve under the standard of liberty.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 December 2; A.L.S. 1p.; Turner, Thomas. Croisic
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 December 3; A.L.S. 1p.; Le Maire de Gimel, Jacques. Nantes
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 December 3; A.L.S. 1p.; Thiery, -----. Paris
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 December 4; A.L.S. 2p.; Gates, Horatio. Boston
    Chevalier de Raimondis, late Captain of the "Cæsar," one of Comte d'Estaing's squadron, had the misfortune to lose his arm in an engagement off the coast; his subsequent stay in Boston, and the presentation to him by the Council of Massachusetts of a fine sword; hopes he will be generously rewarded for his sufferings and heroic behavior. The enemy likely to evacuate New York and Rhode Island.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 December 5; A.L.S. 2p.; Farley, Henry. Paris
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 December 5; A.L.S. 1p.; Clark, Elisha. Bolbec
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 December 5; A.L.S. 2p.; Bondfield, John. Bordeaux
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 December 7; A.L.S. 2p.; Vernon, William. Boston
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 December 8; A.L.S. 1p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 December 8; A.L.S. 2p.; Lovell, James. Philadelphia
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 December 9; A.L.S. 3p.; Lee, William. Frankfort
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 December 9; A.L.S. 3p.; Jones, Capt. John Paul. L'Orient
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 December 9; A.L.S. 1p.; Gourlade and Moylan. L'Orient
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 December 10; A.L.S. 1p.; Hartley, David. London
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 December 10; Mem. 2p.; Denward, Thomas
    Urging the necessity of having an agent in London, and recommending Captain Robinson for the position. Dietary for prisoners.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 December 10; L.S. 3p.; Greene, William. Warwick, R. I
    Enclosing some bills of exchange which he begs Franklin to lay out for him and his son-in law, Major Samuel Ward; the latter's desire to receive consignments of cargoes from merchants in France. Recommending to Franklin's kindness Mr. William Vernon, Jr., now in France, for the purpose of studying the language. Family news.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 December 11; A.L.S. 1p.; Abercromby, John. Bordeaux
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 December 11; A.L.S. 1p.; Thiery, -----. Paris
    Desires to know if Franklin has received a letter of advice concerning the bill of exchange mentioned in his last letter.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 December 11; A.L.S. Fra[nci]s Hopkinson. 1p.; The Treasurer of Loans. Philadelphia
    Notification of bills of exchange furnished to the States of Pennsylvania New Jersey.
  - to Messrs. Franklin and Adams., 1778 December 12; A.L.S. 8p.; D'Acosta frères. Nantes
    Encloses copies of their letters written to Arthur Lee, with his reply; their object in sending them is not to complain of their colleague, but to guard against future misrepresentation.
    (Copies in French of a rather acrid correspondence between Messiura D'Acosta and Mr. Arthur Lee concerning the packing of certain articles bound for Virgina.)
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 December 12; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Concerning a mistake by which Mr. Deane's goods were shipped to America by Mr. Schweighauser.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 December 12; L.S. 1p.; Trumbull, Jonathan. Lebanon
    Introducing Colonel Driks, from Holland; he has served with reputation and honor in the defense of America and has leave of absence to settle his affairs.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 December 12; A.L.S. 2p. A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Philip, -----. Bordeaux
    Begging Franklin to obtain from M. de Sartine, a special dispensation that he may be exempted from service on the King's ships; desires this in order to accept command of a merchant ship bound for Charleston.
    A. E. by Franklin. As a stranger in France, begs to be excused from troubling the Ministers with solicitation for persons unknown to him, and in affairs of which he is ignorant.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 December 13; A.L.S. 2p.; Polignac, Louis-Héraclius-Melchior, vicomte de. Soleure
    Recommending M. de Weiss Daillens.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 December 13; A.L.S. 4p.; Randerath, - de Bermans, baronne. Bouquenom
    Her husband forced by illness to give up his service to the Elector Palatine; their small resources; impossible to take her huband to Aix; applies to franklin for assistance; places her hopes in the fact that her husband and Franklin are both Masons, though belonging to different lodges.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 December 14; A.L.S. 1p.; Gunnison, Benjamin. Roscoff
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 December 14; L. 4p.; J -----, F-----. Heidelberg